Inventory of the Houstater Family Papers 1842-1941
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Houstater Family Papers 1842-1941
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2009.264
0.60
Houstater, Henry F., 1837-1862; Houstater, Harriet, 1842-1931 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 06/08/2009.
Custodial History
Collection was held by Harriet Houstater. After her death, her sister Sarah Houstater owned it.
Biographical Note
Henry F. Houstater was born on 24 June, 1837 in Cambria TWP, Niagara, NY and died 29 October, 1862 in Sandy Hook, Washington, MD. He was buried at Mount View Cemetery, Pekin, Niagara, NY. His father was Jacob "Isiah" Houstater, born 4 August, 1802 and his mother Belinda Gould, born 2 February, 1809 in NY.On September 18, 1861, he enlisted, at Lockport; mustered in as private, Battery M, 1st Regiment, Light Artillery, October 14, 1861, to serve three years. He was appointed corporal, October 14, 1861; sergeant, February 6, 1862; and died, October 29, 1862, at Sandy Hook, Maryland. Politically, he affiliated with the Democratic party. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/Henry F. Houstater.
Scope and Contents
Papers of the Houstater Family, primarily of Henry Houstater (1837-1862) and Harriet (Hattie) Houstater (1842-1931) of New York State. Collection was held by Harriet Houstater. After her death, her sister Sarah Houstater owned it.Collection includes the papers of Henry F. Houstater, a Democrat who enlisted in the Union Army in 1861. Also contains the papers of several Houstater family members. Henry F. Houstater's papers (1840s-1862) include political speeches and literary manuscripts written before the Civil War. During the war, Henry wrote and received several letters and he also wrote several political essays and produced a handwritten newspaper, the Camp Barry Herald.Other family members' papers consist of correspondence and financial documents.
Arrangement of Materials
Organized into two series: Series 1: Houstater Financial Documents and Series 2: Houstater Correspondence and Writings; Newspapers; Envelopes.
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Newspapers
Geographic Name:
New York (State)--Social life and customs.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives; United States--History--Civil War--Niagra County, NY
Topical Term:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Sources; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Houstater Financial Documents, 1836-1944; id63972
  - id64205 (Box 1)
    - Bills, Receipts and Related Records, 1862-1931; id60381 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bonds, 1859-1923; id60377 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Deeds and Land Surveys, 1836-1943; id60375 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mortgages and Payments, 1862-1944; id60382 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Taxes and Payments, 1842-1935; id60376 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Wills and Related Records, 1857-1938; id60373 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Houstater Correspondences and Writings; Newspapers; Envelopes, 1862-1931; id63973
  - id64210 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1857-1906; id60383 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Removed Envelopes, 1862-1906; id63974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - id64206 (Box 2)
    - Henry Houstater's Writings, undated; id60387 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Camp Barry Herald, 1861-1862; id60386 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Newspapers, 1862-1864; id60384 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Removed Envelopes Continued, 1862-1906; id63975 (Box 2, Folder 4)